Guide to the Bombing of London During World War II Photograph Collection, 1939-1940 SC.1966.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Bombing of London During World War II Photograph Collection
1939-1940
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Graphic Photo Union
Associated Press of Great Britain
SC.1966.01
143 items
The Bombing of London during World War II Photograph Collection consists of 143 pictures from the early 1940s that visually document the bombing of London by the Nazis known as "The Blitz." Some are dated while most are not. Images were produced by the Associated Press and Graphic Photo Union.
Custodial History
Transferred from the Fines Art Library to Special Collections in 1966.
History
The photographs in this collection depict the bombing of London by the Nazis during the period of World War II known collectively as "The Blitz." This period of the intense bombing of London and other cities began on September 7, 1940 and ended May 16, 1941. Adolph Hitler was preparing for a German invasion of England and ordered the Lutwaffe to target RAF airfields and radar stations. Hitler abandoned these plans and executed an air strike to destroy London, demoralize the population, and force England to surrender to his terms. London sustained bombings for 57 consecutive nights, which resulted in the damage and destruction of more than one million London homes. Other important landmarks, such as hospitals, churches, and Buckingham Palace were targeted during the air raids resulting in significant human casualties. The Blitz ended on May 11, 1941 when Hitler called off the raids in order to move his bombers east in preparation for Germany's invasion of Russia.
On the backs of these photographs contain a stamp stating that copyright is attributed to the Associated Press and the Graphic Photo Union. Nearly all photos have detailed captions typed onto paper and glued to the back. Some photos include "PASSED FOR PUBLICATION BY MINISTRY OF INFORMATION" on the back.
Previous Citation
Bombing of London During World War II Photograph Collection, 1939-1940, SC.1966.01, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
Scope and Content Notes
This collection contains 143 pictures, taken by the Associated Press during the bombing of London throughout 1940-1941. The photographs are arranged in folders, maintaining the original order and numbering system in which they were received from the Frick Fine Arts Library. The majority of the photographs in this collection measure 8 x 10 inches. However, there are a few of smaller size. Most of the photographs are undated.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the Frick Fine Arts Library in 1966.
Black-and-white photographs; London (England) -- History -- Bombardment, 1940-1941 -- Photographs; World War, 1939-1945 -- Great Britain -- Photographs; World War, 1939-1945 -- England -- London -- Photographs; World War, 1939-1945 -- Destruction and pillage -- Great Britain -- Photographs; World War, 1939-1945 -- Aerial operations, German -- Photographs; Elizabeth, Queen, consort of George VI, King of Great Britain -- Photographs; George, King of Great Britain, VI -- Photographs; Churchill, Winston -- Photographs
- A-Z (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biggest raid on the capital, August 9, 1940; 1.
  - Bomb damages Buckingham Palace: King and Queen not there, 2.
  - Night picture of an A.A. unit at work, 3.
  - An elegant evening gown, yes, but it's a very practical siren suit, 4.
  - Home guards keeps watch for raiders in Countyhall's tower, 5.
  - Off to the House during air raid alarm, May 9, 1940; 6.
  - The House of Lords recieved slight damage when a canister bomb was dropped by Nazi raiders, September 14, 1940; 7.
  - London goes to work by boat instead of bus today, September 3, 1940; 8.
  - War without weapons: Steel helmet offers stranglehold, 9.
  - Learning to fight without weapons: Pulling the enemy's leg, 10.
  - Nazi bomb hits Buckingham Palace, 11.
  - London home of the King and Queen bombed: damage to Buckingham Palace during raid, 12.
  - A new night life in London: Siren time in a famous hotel, 13.
  - London bombed but British courage rules unwaveringly, December 9, 1940; 14.
  - Nazi bombs hit Buckingham Palace, 15.
  - Police turn city workers back from bombed areas today, September 9, 1940; 16.
  - How the A. P. cameraman operates during a NAzi raid on London, 17.
  - More London bomb damage, November 9, 1940; 18.
  - Nazi raiders at Buckingham Palace: King and Queen talk to workers amid debris, September 11, 1940; 19.
  - Nazi raiders bomb Buckingham Palace: King and Queen inspect damage, September 1940; 20.
  - Furniture removals from raid damaged houses, 21.
  - Untitled - The crater made by a bomb..., 22.
  - Heroic hospital sister, July 9, 1940; 23.
  - Reighstag bombed by R.A.F. say Germans, November 9, 1940; 24.
  - Smiling soldiers receiving their pay with their extra sixpence at a London depot, 25.
- AA-BH.1647 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Red letter day for the army today: Drawing the first pay increase packet, September 6, 1940; 1.
  - King visits bombed areas, 2.
  - City office workers unable to reach their offices today, 3.
  - Taking on supplies, 4.
  - Destroyer flotilla at exercise - three different photographs with this title, 5.
  - British flag flies above the Italian on captured submarine, 6.
  - Visit of the first lord of the admirality Rt. Hon. A. V. Alexander to a British port, 7.
  - Anti-aircraft guns in Britain - two different photographs with this title, 8.
  - Newfoundland gunners see how the guards do it, 9.
  - Motorcyclist reconnaissance troops - two different photographs with this title, 10.
  - Prime Minister visits Australian and New Zealand troops, 11.
  - Prime Minister visits bombed area, 12.
  - Prime Minister visits bombed area in East End, 13.
  - Premier visits defences - two different photographs with the same title, 14.
- BH.1649-66323 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Premier visits defences, 1.
  - Prime Minister visits defences, 2.
  - Premier visits defences, 3.
  - Rugby International in the desert, 4.
  - More New Zealand airmaen for R.A.F., 5.
  - Activity in the R.A.F., 6.
  - Untitled - The wrecked garage of a depot..., 7.
  - Fleet arm over Norwegian coast - two different photographs with this title, 8.
  - On the South African home front, 9.
  - South Africa arms with the Empire, 10.
  - Ramsgate relies on her tunnels..., 11.
  - Hitler's military objectives, 12.
  - 1,000 in bombed London shelter last night, September 6, 1940; 13.
  - Italian prisoners in Alexandria, 14.
  - London bobby takes a look at crashed Nazi plane, September 6, 1940; 15.
  - Damage caused when bomb dropped at Elephant & Castle, September 6, 1940; 16.
  - Bomb makes big crater..., September 6, 1940; 17.
  - Bomb falls on raid shelter..., 18.
  - Bomb removes front of house, September 6, 1940; 19.
  - Bombs make huge crater..., 20.
  - Church damaged in last night's raid on London, 21.
  - Church bombed in last night's raid on London..., 22.
  - Untitled - Bomb wrecks church in last night's raid on London, 23.
  - Isolation hospital wrecked by bombs, September 7, 1940; 24.
- 66441-67628 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Homeless victims of London air raid seek sanctuary in London school - two different photographs with the same title, 1.
  - Thames reflects back flames, 2.
  - East London homeless move to safety after last night's severe raid, 3.
  - Dockland blaze lights up London sky, 4.
  - Fires in East London Industrial area, September 7, 1940; 5.
  - London's biggest raid, September 8, 1940; 6.
  - After London's biggest raid, 7.
  - Biggest raid of the war on London, September 9, 1940; 8.
  - Biggest raid on the capital, September 9, 1940
  - Damage to London Docklands..., 9.
  - Timber ablaze in London Dockland, 10.
  - Morning after London's biggest raid, 11.
  - Air raid damage in the city of London..., 12.
  - Bus battered in city of London raid, 13.
  - Regent Street's famous quadrant..., 14.
  - An air raid "scarecrow"..., 15.
  - Firemen play water on damaged city building, 16.
  - A hitch-hike to safety..., 17.
  - Little "hitch-hikers", 18.
  - Nurses salvage their property after bombing..., 19.
  - King visits East End and sees..., 20.
  - King visits East End, inspects..., 21.
  - Bomb damage to London hospital, 22.
  - Homeless East Londoners..., 23.
- 67629-70036 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - After London's two biggest raids..., 1.
  - Cinema hit by bomb but waxworks intact, 2.
  - Union Jack still flying..., 3.
  - Maternity hospital bombed..., 4.
  - London fire-fighters save St. Paul's..., 5.
  - Maternity hospital hit..., 6.
  - Children's hospital hit..., 7.
  - Child victim of hospital bombing taken to safety, 8.
  - Saving St. Paul's..., 9.
  - Visited London Theatre..., 10.
  - Bomb makes big crater..., 11.
  - Girl buried under debris inspects damage..., 12.
  - Owner of car "casualty" smiles at the wheel..., 13.
  - Walking to work and still smiling, 14.
  - Bombs damage London's famous Burlington Arcade, December 9, 1940; 15.
  - H.R.H. the Duchess of Kent..., 16.
  - Hole in the wall..., 17.
  - Bomb goes right through..., 18.
  - Bomb crater outside Buckingham Palace..., 19.
  - Damage done to Buckingham Palace chapel..., 20.
  - Damaged quadrangle at Buckingham Palace..., 21.
  - Debris scatted outside Buckingham Palace..., 22.
  - A.R.P. workers searching..., 23.
  - Kitten rescued with her few belongings..., 24.
  - Buckingham Palace again bombed, 25.
- 70090-70685 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Girl saved after being buried under debris for four days, 1.
  - Sisters of Mercy minister to air raid victims, 2.
  - Dornier brought down on London Roof top..., 3.
  - Nazi raider brought down in London Street..., 4.
  - Nazi raider brought down in London during today's raid, 5.
  - Children play with salvaged toy, 6.
  - Building brick castles, 7.
  - Black cat for luck..., 8.
  - Nazis make hospitals their targets..., 9.
  - Evacuating a case from bombed hospital, 10.
  - Hospital damaged by Nazi bombs in last night's raid, 11.
  - Evacuating mothers from bombed London hospital, 12.
  - Famous East London church bombed..., 13.
  - Men who make the barrage - two different photographs with the same title, 14.
  - The men who saved St. Paul's, 15.